and give it to him." My dad has frontotemporal lobe dementia, or FTD. It's a confusing disease that hits people in their 50s or 60s. It can completely change someone's personality, making them paranoid and even violent. My dad's been sick for a decade, but three years ago he got really sick, and we had to move him out of his house -- the house that I grew up in, the house that he built with his own hands. My strapping, cool dad with the falsetto singing voice had to move into a facility for round-the-clock care when he was just 65. At first my mom and sisters and I made the mistake of putting him in a regular nursing home. It was really pretty; it had plush carpet and afternoon art classes and a dog named Diane. But then I got a phone call. "Ms. Malone, we've arrested your father." "What?" "Well, he threatened everybody with cutlery. And then he yanked the curtains off the wall, and then he tried to throw plants out the window. And then, well, he pulled all the old ladies out of their wheelchairs." "All the old ladies?" (Laughter) "What a cowboy." After he got kicked out of there, we bounced him between a bunch of state-run facilities
y dársela". Mi padre tiene demencia del lóbulo frontotemporal o FTD. Es una enfermedad confusa que afecta a personas entre 50 y 60 años. Puede cambiar completamente la personalidad de alguien, haciéndole paranoico e incluso violento. Mi padre ha estado enfermo durante una década, pero hace tres años se puso realmente enfermo, y tuvimos que sacarlo de su casa... la casa en la que crecí, la casa que él construyó con sus propias manos. Mi encantador y musculoso padre, que canta con voz de falsete, tuvo que trasladarse a un centro de atención las 24 horas cuando solo tenía 65 años. Al principio mi madre, mis hermanas y yo cometimos el error de ponerle en una residencia regular. Era realmente bonita; tenía moqueta y clases de arte por las tardes y había una perra llamada Diane. Pero entonces recibí una llamada. "Srta. Malone, hemos arrestado a su padre". "¿Qué?" "Bueno, él ha amenazado a todos con los cuchillos. Y ha arrancado las cortinas de las paredes, y ha intentado lanzar las plantas por la ventana. Y, bueno, él ha tirado a todas las ancianas de sus sillas de ruedas". "¿A todas las ancianas?" (Risas) "Menudo vaquero". Después de expulsado de allí, fuimos probando entre varios centros estatales
before finding a treatment center specifically for people with dementia. At first, he kind of liked it, but over time his health declined, and one day I walked in and found him sitting hunched over on the ground wearing a onesie -- those kinds of outfits that zip in the back. I watched him for about an hour as he yanked at it,
hasta encontrar un centro de tratamiento específico para personas con demencia. Al principio, más o menos, le gustaba, pero con el tiempo su salud empeoró, y un día al entrar me lo encontré sentado ovillado en el suelo con un mono... del tipo que tienen la cremallera en la espalda. Lo observé durante una hora mientras trataba de liberarse,
trying to find a way out of this thing.
buscando una forma de quitarse esa cosa.
And it's supposed to be practical, but to me it looked like a straightjacket. And so I ran out. I left him there. I sat in my truck -- his old truck -- hunched over, this really deep guttural cry coming out of the pit of my belly. I just couldn't believe that my father, the Adonis of my youth, my really dear friend, would think that this kind of life was worth living anymore. We're programmed to prioritize productivity. So when a person -- an Adonis in this case -- is no longer productive in the way we expect him to be, the way that he expects himself to be, what value does that life have left? That day in the truck, all I could imagine was that my dad was being tortured and his body was the vessel of that torture. I've got to get him out of that body. I've got to get him out of that body; I'm going to kill Dad. I call my sister. "Beth," she said. "You don't want to live the rest of your life knowing that you killed your father. And you'd be arrested I think, because he can't condone it. And you don't even know how to buy heroin." (Laughter) It's true, I don't. The truth is we talk about his death a lot. When will it happen? What will it be like? But I wish that we would have talked about death when we were all healthy. What does my best death look like? What does your best death look like? But my family didn't know to do that. And my sister was right. I shouldn't murder Dad with heroin, but I've got to get him out of that body. So I went to a psychic. And then a priest, and then a support group, and they all said the same thing: sometimes people hang on when they're worried about loved ones. Just tell them you're safe, and it's OK to go when you're ready. So I went to see Dad. I found him hunched over on the ground in the onesie. He was staring past me and just kind of looking at the ground. I gave him a ginger ale and just started talking about nothing in particular, but as I was talking, he sneezed from the ginger ale.
Y se supone que debe de ser práctico, pero para mí era como una camisa de fuerza. Y entonces hui. Le abandoné allí. Me senté en mi furgoneta -- su antiguo furgoneta -- me hice una bola, con este profundo y gutural llanto que surgía del fondo de mi estomago. Sencillamente no podía creer que mi padre, el Adonis de mi juventud, mi queridísimo amigo, pudiese creer que este tipo de vida mereciese la pena ser vivida. Estamos programados para priorizar la productividad. Así que cuando una persona -- un Adonis en este caso -- ya no es productivo de la manera que se espera de él, de la forma en la que él mismo espera ser, ¿qué valor tiene esa vida? Ese día en la furgoneta, todo en lo que podía pensar era que mi padre estaba siendo torturado y que su cuerpo era la cárcel para esa tortura. Tengo que liberarlo de ese cuerpo. Tengo que sacarlo de ese cuerpo; voy a matar a papá. Llamé a mi hermana. "Beth", dijo, "no quieres vivir el resto de tu vida sabiendo que has matado a tu padre. Y probablemente te arrestarán, porque él no puede absolverte. Y tú ni siquiera sabes cómo comprar heroína". (Risas) Es cierto, no lo sé. Lo cierto es que hablamos mucho sobre su muerte. ¿Cuándo ocurrirá? ¿Cómo será? Pero desearía que hubiésemos hablado sobre la muerte cuando aún estábamos bien. ¿Cómo sería mi muerte ideal? ¿Cómo sería tu muerte ideal? Pero mi familia no supo hacer eso. Y mi hermana tenía razón. No debía asesinar a mi padre con heroína, pero tenía que sacarlo de ese cuerpo. Así que fui a un psíquico. Y después a un sacerdote, y luego a un grupo de apoyo, y todos dijeron lo mismo: a veces las personas aguantan cuando están preocupadas por los que aman. Solo dile que está a salvo, y que está bien que se vaya cuando esté listo. Así que fui a ver a papá. Lo encontré acurrucado en el suelo con el mono. Estaba mirando más allá de mí y solo mirando el suelo. Le di una cerveza de jengibre y simplemente empezamos a hablar sobre nada en particular, pero mientras le hablaba, estornudó por la cerveza de jengibre.
And the sneeze -- it jerked his body upright, sparking him back to life a little bit. And he just kept drinking and sneezing and sparking, over and over and over again until it stopped. And I heard, "Heheheheheh, heheheheheh ... this is so fabulous. This is so fabulous." His eyes were open and he was looking at me, and I said, "Hi, Dad!" and he said, "Hiya, Beth." And I opened my mouth to tell him, right? "Dad, if you want to die, you can die. We're all OK." But as I opened my mouth to tell him, all I could say was, "Dad! I miss you." And then he said, "Well, I miss you, too." And then I just fell over because I'm just a mess. So I fell over and I sat there with him because for the first time in a long time he seemed kind of OK. And I memorized his hands, feeling so grateful that his spirit was still attached to his body. And in that moment I realized I'm not responsible for this person. I'm not his doctor, I'm not his mother, I'm certainly not his God, and maybe the best way to help him and me is to resume our roles as father and daughter. And so we just sat there, calm and quiet like we've always done. Nobody was productive. Both of us are still strong. "OK, Dad. I'm going to go, but I'll see you tomorrow." "OK," he said. "Hey, this is a pretty nice hacienda." Thank you. (Applause)
Y ese estornudo le estremeció todo el cuerpo, devolviéndole un poco a la vida. Y simplemente siguió bebiendo, estornudando y volviendo, una y otra y otra vez hasta que paró. Y escuché: "Je, je, je, je, je, je, je, je, je, je, je, je... esto es tan fabuloso. Esto es tan fabuloso". Sus ojos estaban abiertos y me estaba mirando, y dije: "¡Hola, papá!" y él dijo: "Hiya, Beth". Y abrí la boca para decírselo, ¿no? "Papá, si quieres morir, puedes morir. Nosotras estamos bien". Pero al abrir la boca para decírselo, todo lo que pude decir fue, "¡Papá! Te echo de menos". Y él respondió: "Bien, yo también te hecho de menos". Y entonces simplemente me desmoroné porque soy un desastre. Me desmoroné y me senté con él porque por primera vez en mucho tiempo él parecía estar bien. Y memoricé sus manos, sintiéndome tan agradecida de que su espíritu siguiese unido a su cuerpo. Y en ese momento me di cuenta de que no era responsable de esta persona. No soy su médico, no soy su madre, por supuesto no soy su Dios, y puede que la mejor manera de ayudarle, a él y a mí, era recuperar nuestros roles como padre e hija. Y simplemente nos sentamos allí, tranquilos y callados como siempre hemos hecho. Nadie era productivo. Ambos aún somos fuertes. "Vale papá. Me tengo que ir, pero te veré mañana". "Vale", dijo. "Oye, esta hacienda está bastante bien". Gracias. (Aplausos)